Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts, 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0744.03
Manuscripts Division
Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts
1600s-1900s
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Garrett, Robert, b. 1875
C0744.03
82 boxes
39 items
23.3 linear feet
Consists of 113 bound manuscripts with texts in Ge'ez and occasionally Amharic, forming part of the Robert Garrett Collection (C0744).
Scope and Contents
The Robert Garrett Collection contains 113 Ethiopic codices (bound manuscripts), which are chiefly written in Ge'ez, the sacred and liturgical Afro-Asiatic language of Ethiopian Orthodox Christians. Some texts are in Amharic. Included among Ethiopic manuscripts at Princeton are Bibles, Gospels, Psalters, homilies, liturgy, saints' lives and miracles, theology, law, compilations on magic and divination, and other texts. Pseudepigraphic manuscripts include the Book of Enoch, which was used in R. H. Charles, ed., The Book of Enoch, Translated from Professor Dillmann's Ethiopic Text... (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1893). A modest number of the manuscripts are illuminated. The two earliest manuscripts date from the 17th century: Garrett Ethiopic no. 1 (Bible) and no. 2 (Dersana Mika'el), both from the library of the Emperor Theodore (r. 1855-1868) of Ethiopia. However, most of the manuscripts at Princeton date from the 18th and 19th centuries. Texts are written in black ink on parchment. The quires are bound in a traditional style reminiscent of early Christian codices. The manuscripts are sewn with unsupported link-stitch and then laced into rough-hewn wooden boards or sometimes covered in blind-tooled leather. A number of manuscripts are in leather carrying cases, which allowed them to be worn over the shoulder or hung up on pegs in walls.
Arrangement
Organized into one series by shelf number:
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Texts are written in black ink on parchment. The quires are bound in a traditional style reminiscent of early Christian codices. The manuscripts are sewn with unsupported link-stitch and then laced into rough-hewn wooden boards or sometimes covered in blind-tooled leather. A number of manuscripts are in leather carrying cases, which allowed them to be worn over the shoulder or hung up on pegs in walls. The wooden covers of some codices are broken, and the stitching on some of the spines is deteriorating.
Custodial History
Garrett acquired 101 Ethiopic codices from Enno Littmann (1875-1958). Garrett acquired a dozen more codices from other sources. Many of the original owners' names appear on the manuscripts, occasionally in the form of specialized prayers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The manuscripts were given to Princeton University Library by Robert Garrett (1875-1961) in 1942. Garrett acquired 101 Ethiopic codices and 147 magic scrolls from Enno Littmann (1875-1958), who lead a Princeton expedition to Tigray, Ethiopia, in the autumn of 1905 (with Garrett's financial backing) and a German expedition to Aksum (Deutsche Aksum-Expedition) in the first few months of 1906. Littmann was an eminent German scholar who, during his long academic career, taught at Princeton, Strassburg, Göttingen, Bonn, and Tübingen. Most of the bound manuscripts and magic scrolls that Littmann collected in northern Ethiopia are at Princeton, but other manuscripts are in Germany (Berlin; Halle-an-der-Salle). Garrett acquired a dozen more codices from other sources.
Appraisal
No appraisal information is available.
Related Materials
In addition to the 113 Garrett Ethiopic codices, the Library also has an open collection called Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts (C0776), acquired individually by gift or purchase. Since the 1990s, Bruce C. Willsie, Princeton Class of 1986, has been the principal donor. There is one Ethiopic manuscript in The Scheide Library (Manuscript 119).
The Library also has three substantial collections of Ethiopic magic scrolls. Professor David Appleyard, School of Oriental and African Studies, London, compiled the online checklist of these scrolls, with support from the David A. Gardner '69 Magic Project, Princeton University.
Garrett, Robert, b. 1875
Biographical / Historical
Robert Garrett was born in Baltimore, Maryland, on June 24, 1875. Garrett inherited his collecting interest from his father, Thomas Harrison Garrett, Princeton Class of 1868. After his father's sudden death in 1888, Garrett spent the following two and a half years traveling extensively with his mother and two brothers, Horatio and John, in Europe and the Near East. During his travels Garrett developed a particular interest in manuscripts and began collecting. He used the text Universal Paleography: or, Fac-similes of Writing of All Nations and Periods by J. B. Silvestre (tr. by Sir Frederic Madden, London, 1949-50) as his guide for collecting primary examples of every known type of script. Garrett returned to the United States in 1891 and soon after began his studies at Princeton University. He received his A.B. degree from Princeton in 1897. While in school, Garrett excelled in track and field athletics. In 1896 he competed in the first modern Olympic games in Athens, Greece, where he became the first champion in discus and shot put. After graduation he continued on in the family banking firm, Robert Garrett & Sons, in Baltimore, Maryland. However, he maintained very close contact with his alma mater and in 1905 was elected a Life Trustee of Princeton University. Throughout his career Garrett also remained dedicated to his collecting hobby. He maintained from the beginning that his collection would one day be given to the Princeton University Library so that it would always be connected with academic research. He donated the bulk of his collection to the Princeton University Library in 1942. Robert Garrett died on April 25, 1961, in Baltimore, Maryland. In the end he had amassed a collection of over 11,000 volumes of Western and non-Western manuscripts, fragments, and scrolls, originating from Europe, the Near East, Africa, Asia and Mesoamerica, ca. 1340 B.C.-1900s.
Bibliography
Ephraim Isaac, "Princeton Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts," Princeton University Library Chronicle 42:1 (Autumn 1980), pp. 33-52. Richard Pankhurst, "Secular Themes in Ethiopian Ecclesiastical Manuscripts: V.: A Catalogue of Illustrations of Historical and Ethnographic Interest in Princeton University Library and Art Gallery," Journal of Ethiopian Studies 22 (November 1989), pp. 31-64. Don C. Skemer, "Princeton's Ethiopic Manuscript Collections at 100," Princeton University Library Chronicle 71:3 (Spring 2010), pp. 461-466.
Manuscripts, Ethiopic.; Liturgical books--Ethiopia.; Orthodox Eastern Church--Liturgy--Texts.
- Series 1: Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts (C0744.03), 1570-1950; 82 boxes; 39 items
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of 113 bound manuscripts in Ge'ez and Amharic.
  Arrangement
  Organized by shelf number.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 1: The Four Gospels, 1650-1699; 1; 1 box Parchment. 141 folios; 3 columns, 25 lines. Wooden boards covered and bound with full stamped leather. The insides of the covers have square pink brocade inserts 42 x 37 cm
    Endnotes: various, fols. 3r-5v, mostly inventories pertaining to the church of St. Giyorgis; mention of King Iyo'as (r. 1755-69). Endnotes referring to King Egwāla S'eyon (r. 1801-18) and King Sāhla Dengel (r. 1832-55) fol. 14v. Endnote referring to King Tēwodros II (r. 1855-68) fol. 135v. Various endnotes fols.136v-139r, referring to King Sāhla Dengel (r. 1832-55), King Tēwodros II (r. 1855-68), King Iyo'as (r. 1755-69), also unspecified King Iyāsu (I r. 1682-1706, II r. 1730-55, III r. 1784-88); including list of clergy of the church of St. Giyorgis and inventories of the property of and gifts to the same.
    - Introduction to the Gospels, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 6r-9v (Box 1)
    - Canon Tables, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 10r-13v (Box 1)
    - Inventory of Gospel of Matthew, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 14r-v (Box 1)
    - Gospel of Matthew in Eighty-One Chapters, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 15r-50r (Box 1)
    - Inventory of Gospel of Mary, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 50v (Box 1)
    - Gospel of Mark in Forty-Nine Chapters, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 50v-73r (Box 1)
    - Inventory of Gospel of Luke, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 73v (Box 1)
    - Gospel of Luke in Seventy-Eight Chapters, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 74r-107v (Box 1)
    - Inventory of Gospel of John, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 107v (Box 1)
    - Gospel of John in Forty-Five Chapters, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 107v-135v (Box 1)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 2: Homilies of the Archangel Michael and Associated Texts, 1700-1730; 2; 1 box Parchment. 101 folios, 2 columns, 19 lines. 23 paintings. Wooden boards covered with stamped leather. Fols. 18v, 19v, 35v, 51r, 58v, 63v, 77r, 84v, 85r, 90r, 95r blank 28.5 x 25 cm
    Various endnotes fol. 1r.
    Note in English that the manuscript was taken from the fortress of King Theodore (Tēwodros II) at Magdala in 1868 fol. 1v.
    Paintings:
    God the Father as the Ancient of Days fol. 10r.
    St. Michael subduing the devil fol. 10v.
    St. Michael bringing souls out of hell fol. 11r.
    St. Michael leading souls into paradise fol. 11v.
    [top] Dorātyos selling his wife's garment in exchange for a sheep, and [bottom] St. Michael appears to Dorātyos in the guise of a nobleman fol. 18r.
    [top] Dorātyos bringing the sheep and a fish to St. Michael, and [bottom] Dorātyos holding a feast on St. Michael's day fol. 19r.
    Talāfinos's mother gleaning in the nobleman's field fol. 28v.
    [top] Talāfinos's mother giving her infant to the nobleman, and [bottom] the nobleman giving her a letter announcing that her child is dead after he placed it in a chest in the sea fol. 29r.
    [top] of St. Michael addressing her and her reading the letter, and [bottom] of her grinding corn outside the church which she had had built for St. Michael fol. 29v.
    [top] of the poor man praying to St. Michael, and [bottom] throwing a chest into the sea containing the gold he owed his creditor fol. 35r.
    [top] of the creditor cutting open the fish and finding the chest, and [bottom] the two men meeting and discussing the miracle fol. 36r.
    Qison asleep outside the church and then asking for hymns to be sung on St. Michael's day fol. 50v.
    [top] of the bishop baptizing Qison and his family, and [bottom] their departure by sea fol. 51v.
    [top] of Moses asking Pharaoh to release his people, and [bottom] St. Michael showing the Israelites the way across the Red Sea fol. 58r.
    Pharaoh's army drowning in the Red Sea fol. 59r.
    John Chrysostom telling Eudoxia the wife of Emperor Arcadius not to take communion fol. 63r.
    Eudoxia's messengers finding John Chrysostom fol. 64r.
    [top] Satan tempting Afomyā and her praying to St. Michael, and [bottom] St. Michael transfixing Satan fol. 77v.
    [top] Talāson and the rich man bargaining for the sale of the sheep, and the shepherd finding the sheep in a sack in the sea, and [bottom] his encounter with St. Michael who exchanges the letter of death for a letter of life, and his wife holds a wedding feast fol. 84r.
    [top] the prophet Daniel questioning the elders and saving Susannah, and [bottom] St. Michael cleaving in two the elders fol. 89v.
    St. Michael hanging Satan in the church fol. 90v.
    The blind man praying to St. Michael in the church fol.94v.
    [top] God sending the Angel of Death to the idolater, and [bottom] the Angel of Death retrieving his soul from the chest in which he had been thrown into the sea fol. 95v.
    Former owners: Sars'a Dengel and his wife Walatta P'ēt'ros.
    - 12th of Hedār (Nov. 21), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Hedār (Nov. 21) by Abbā Damātēwos of Alexandria, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 2r-6v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 6v-7v (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Hedār 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 8r-9r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 9r-v (Box 2)
    - 12th of Tāhsās (Dec. 21), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Tāhsās (Dec. 21), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 12r-16v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 16v-17r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Tāhsās 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 17r-v (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 17v (Box 2)
    - 12th of T'er (Jan. 20), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of T'er (Jan. 20), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 20r-27r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 27v-28r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for T'er 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 28r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 28r (Box 2)
    - Yakkātit (Feb. 19), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Yakkātit (Feb. 19), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 30r-32v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 32v-34r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Yakkātit 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 34r-v (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 34v (Box 2)
    - Maggābit (Mar. 21), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Maggābit (Mar. 21) by Severus Bishop of Antioch, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 36v-49r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 49r-50r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Maggābit 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 50r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 50r (Box 2)
    - Miyāzyā (Apr. 20), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Miyāzyā (Apr. 20) by "the Orthodox", early 18th century; 1 box Folio 52r-55v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 55v-57r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Miyāzyā 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 57r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 57v (Box 2)
    - Genbot (May 20), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Genbot (May 20) by John Bishop of Ethiopia, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 59v-60v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 60v-62r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Genbot 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 62r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 62r-v (Box 2)
    - Sanē (June 19), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Sanē (June 19) by the Bishop of Axum, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 64v-69v (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 69v-71r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Sanē 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 71r-76v (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 76v-77r (Box 2)
    - Hamlē (Jul. 19), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Hamlē (Jul. 19), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 78v-82r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 82r-83r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Hamlē 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 83r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 83v (Box 2)
    - Nahasē (Aug. 18), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily the 12th of Nahasē (Aug. 18) Written "in Jerusalem", early 18th century; 1 box Folio 85v-88r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 88r-v (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Nahasē 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 88v-89r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 89r (Box 2)
    - Maskaram (Sept. 22), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of Maskaram (Sept. 22), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 91r-93r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 93r-v (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for Maskaram 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 94r (Box 2)
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 94r. (Box 2)
    - T'eqemt (Oct. 22), 1700-1730; 1 box
      - Homily for the 12th of T'eqemt (Oct. 22), early 18th century; 1 box Folio 96r-99r (Box 2)
      - Miracle of St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 99r-101r (Box 2)
      - Synaxarium Entry for T'eqemt 12, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 101r (Box 2)
        Concluding with blessings upon the original owners or donors
      - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to St. Michael, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 101v (Box 2)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 3: Organ of Praise of the Virgin Mary (Argānona Weddāsē), 1750-1800; 3; 1 box Parchment. 125 folios; 2 columns, 18 lines 22 x 25 cm
    Various endnotes: Prayer and Legend of St. Susenyos, fol. 1v; a short theological treatise, partially stained, fol. 2r-3v.
    - Argānona Weddāsē, With Sections for Monday Through Sunday, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 4r-118v (Box 3)
    - An Inserted Folio With Endnotes in Amharic and Ge'ez Recording Transactions, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 112 (Box 3)
    - A theological Speculation on the Nature of Religious Piety, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 118v-120r (Box 3)
    - A Fragment of a Malke'a Lalibalā, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 120r-125v (Box 3)
      (in a later hand)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 4: Organ of Praise of the Virgin Mary (Argānona Weddāsē), 1750-1800; 4; 1 box Parchment. 139 folios; 2 columns, 17 lines. Staining to the top of most leaves. Wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fols. 1r-v and 139r-v are blank 25 x 27.5 cm
    Former owners: Walda Abiyya Egzi' and Gabra Egzi'abehēr.
    - A Personal Prayer in Verse to Mary, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 2r-4v (Box 4)
    - Argānona Weddās, With Sections for Monday Through Sunday, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 5r-136r (Box 4)
    - A Personal Prayer and Petition in the Name of Gabra Egzi'abehēr, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 81r-v (Box 4)
      Different hand.
    - Liturgical Fragment, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 136v-137r (Box 4)
    - Another Fragment of the Liturgy, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 137v (Box 4)
      Different hand. With cantillation signs.
    - Further Fragment, 1750-1800; 1 box Folio 138r-v (Box 4)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 5: Pauline Epistles, late 18th century; 5; 1 item Parchment. 86 folios; 2 columns, 23 lines. Wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fol. 86v is blank 25 x 28 cm (Box 5)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 6: Writings of Cyril of Alexandria, 1770-1830; 6; 1 box Parchment. 86 folios, 3 columns, 29 lines. Wooden boards, double hide case with strap. 25 x 25 cm
    Pen trials fols.1r-2v.
    There are minor emendations and notes throughout by a later scribe named as Walda Gabre'ēl.
    - Various Writings of Cyril (Qērellos), late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-85r (Box 6)
      Chapter headings and section markers, etc., in red.
    - List of offices for the Month of Maskaram, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 85v-86r (Box 6)
      Later hand.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 7: Bible: Various Old Testament Books, 1570-1630; 7; 1 box Parchment. 148 folios; 3 columns, 29 lines. Wooden boards, stitched spine covered with leather. 21 x 24.5 cm
    Various endnotes and pen trials fols. 143v-144v and 145r; liturgical extract with cantillation signs fol. 147r-v.
    - Book of Job, late 16th or early 17th century; 1 box Folio 5r-19v (Box 7)
    - Proverbs of Solomon, late 16th or early 17th century; 1 box Folio 19v-52r (Box 7)
    - Song of Songs, late 16th or early 17th century; 1 box Folio 52r-86v (Box 7)
    - Minor Prophets, late 16th or early 17th century; 1 box Folio 87r-128r (Box 7)
      Hosea fols. 87r-92r. Amos 92r-96v. Micah 96v-99v. Joel 99v-101r. Obadiah 101v-102r. Jonah 102r-103r. Nahum 103r-104r. Habakkuk 104r-105v. Zephaniah 105v-107r. Haggai 107r-108v. Zechariah 108v-114v. Malachi 114v-116v. Daniel 116v-128r.
    - Ezra, late 16th or early 17th century; 1 box Folio 128r-143v (Box 7)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 8: Fragment of the Judgment of Kings (Fetha Nagast), late 17th or early 18thcentury; 8; 1 item Parchment. 115 folios; 2 columns, 24 lines. No covers, stitched spine 20 x 23.5 cm (Box 8)
    Book of the Judgement of Kings (Fetha Nagast) Part II (kefel dāgem) fols. 1r-115r, chapters 23 through 51.
    Fols. 110-115 detached.
    Articles 46 and 51 are incomplete and finish in abrupto. Each chapter, articl, and subdivision is indicated in red.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 9: Praise of God, Organ of Praise of the Virgin Mary, and Other Texts, 1650-1699; 9; 1 box Parchment. 169 folios; 2 columns, 21 lines. Wooden boards with leather spine and patterned cloth cover, along with a hide case and strap. 17 x 18.5 cm
    Various endnotes fol. 1r; Russian Orthodox printed pictures sewn to the leaf fol. 1v. Exegesis on the Creation story fols. 2r-3v.
    Former owner: original name erased and replaced by Kefla Māryām and later (in purple ink) by Gabra Yohannes.
    Pen trials fol. 169r.
    - Text Known as the Weddāsē Amlāk (Praise of God), 1650-1699; 1 box
      - Prayers and Supplications by Basil of Caesarea for Monday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 4r-14v (Box 9)
      - Prayers by Ephraim the Syrian for Tuesday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 14v-31r (Box 9)
      - Prayers Drawn from Homilies by Ephraim the Syrian for Wednesday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 31r-43v (Box 9)
      - Prayers by Abba Sinoda the Abbot for Friday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 60r-71v (Box 9)
      - Prayers by Cyril of Alexandria for Sunday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 80v-90v (Box 9)
      - Prayers by St. John Aragāwi Manfasāwi (John of Saba) for Thursday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 44r-60r (Box 9)
      - Prayers by Athanasius of Alexandria for Saturday, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 71v-80v (Box 9)
      - Prayer to Jesus, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 90v-91v (Box 9)
    - Organ of Praise of the Virgin Mary (Argānona Weddāsē) Divided Into Section for the Days of the Week, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 92r-166r (Box 9)
    - Prayers to the Virgin Mary and to the Eucharist, second half of the 17th century; 1 box Folio 166v-168v (Box 9)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 10: The Judgment of Kings (Fetha Nagast), 1770-1830; 10; 1 box Parchment. 151 folios; 3 columns, 30-32 lines. Wooden boards covered with leather and plain cloth over-sleeve 18.5 x 23.5 cm
    Endnote: inventory fol. 150v.
    - Penitential Canon, late 18th/early 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-2v (Box 10)
    - The Judgement of Kings (Fetha Nagast), late 18th/early 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-150v (Box 10)
      There are occasional emendations and explanatory notes in Amharic in the margins. Concluding section and colophon mentioning King Yohannes (along with dates according to various eras, none of which corresponds to the reign of any of the four kings named Yohannes) fol. 150r-v.
    - Part of a Pentitential Canon, late 18th/early 19th century; 1 box Folio 151r (Box 10)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 11: Homilies and Prayers to Jesus Christ, 1700-1730; 11; 1 box Parchment. 138 folios; 2 columns, 14 lines. Wooden boards coverd in red stamped leather. Fols. 1r-4v and 135v-138v are blank 17 x 24 cm
    Ornamental harags (head- and margin-ornament) at the beginning of each day's readings.